本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:东吾 king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
Kishuu Province
嘆かずともよい
Do not weep.
Soon, you will be in paradise.
すぐに極楽浄土へ旅立ってるんだ
南無阿弥陀仏
Praise to Amida Buddha.
おや　兄上はまだそれだけしかお救いになっていないのですか
Is that all you have saved, Brother?
Ten Crucifix Insects
Miyoshi Seikai Nyuudou
Praise to Amida Buddha.
南無阿弥陀仏
Ten Crucifix Insects
Miyoshi Isa Nyuudou
わたくしはすでに20人ほど救って差し上げましたよ
I have already saved twenty.
数などどうでもよいことでしょう
The number is not what is important.
この勤めは　村を潰すという我が幸村様より賜った大事な命なのですよ
The task of destroying this village
was given to us by our master, Yukimura-sama.
Ten Crucifix Insects
Yuri Kamanosuke
Kakei Juuzou
然り
Indeed.
これだけ死体がありゃ十分だろうよ
These are more than enough corpses.
では頼みます　穴山殿
Then, take care of it, Anayama-dono.
Ten Crucifix Insects
Anayama Kosuke
Very well.
分かった
ジャスティス
Justice!
我ら十傑蟲の血の狼煙
The bloody beacon of the Ten Crucifix Insects.
届け　幸村様の元へ
May it reach Yukimura-sama.
To Kishuu! The Ten Crucifix
Insects of Sanada Appear!
【いざ紀州へ　真田十傑蟲　現る】
Edo Castle
江戸を襲った蟲人に関して　ご報告申し上げます
Here's the report on the
Insect-man that attacked Edo.
Eighth Shogun
Tokugawa Yoshimune
まさか蟲人襲来の報告とは
I can't believe the Insect-men attacked...
蟲奉行様もおられるわけだ
And the Insect Magistrate is here.
しかし　夏は過ぎたとは言え
But even though summer is over,
is her body's poison safe?
体より溢れる瘴気は大丈夫なのか
蟲人は昨日酉の刻　江戸に突如飛来
Late yesterday afternoon,
the Insect-man appeared in Edo.
多数の町人に手をかけましたが
It claimed many lives, but...
月島流　富岳鉄槌割
Tsukishima-style: Mt. Fuji Hammer!
そうか　蟲奉行所が
I see... The Magistrate's Office defeated it.
蟲奉行所は被害が広がる前に対処できなかったのか
Could the Office not defeat it
before the damage spread?
彼らは健闘したと言えるでしょう
They performed admirably.
三年前の大阪遠征では
The army that engaged them three years ago,
討伐隊が全滅したのですから
in the Oosaka expedition, was destroyed.
毛利勝永と名乗る一人の蟲人のために
A single Insect-man,
Mouri Katsunaga, defeated them.
報告によれば　自らを猿飛佐助と名乗ったそうです
This report says it called
itself Sarutobi Sasuke.
猿飛　あの真田幸村の家臣ではないか
Sarutobi?
That's a retainer of Sanada Yukimura!
毛利にしろ真田にしろ　遠の昔に死んだはずだろう
A century ago, both Mouri and Sanada died!
やはりそうだ　奴らは百年前の亡霊なんだ
I knew it...
They're spirits from a century ago!
Edo is finished...
このままでは江戸はもう
Be not afraid!
案ずるな
We have the Insect Magistrate!
我々には　蟲奉行殿がおる
蟲奉行殿はお籠もりで気力も能力も万全とした
By sealing herself away, she has
refreshed herself and her powers anew.
そのお力と策を持ってすれば
With her mind and her powers,
those insects are nothing to fear!
あのような蟲など恐れるに足りん
うむ　すべてわらわに任せるがよい
Yes.
Leave everything to me.
なんと頼もしい
That's wonderful!
そうじゃ　われわれには蟲奉行殿がおられるではないか
Indeed...
We have the Insect Magistrate on our side!
Princess, I apologize for having
involved you in such a farce,
老中たちを安心させるためとは言え
あのような茶番を
誠に申し訳ありませぬ　姫君
even if we did need
to keep the ministers calm.
気を揉むな　あの程度のこと　なんでもない
Do not concern yourself.
It was nothing.
し　しかし今の姫は
However, even now, you...
The insects, the Insect-men...
蟲にしろ　蟲人にしろ
their appearance is entirely my responsibility.
奴らが現われるようになったのは　何もかもわらわ一人の責任
力を失ったこの身なれど
I may have lost my power,
命をかけて
but I am willing to sacrifice
my life to end this!
わらわがすべてを終わらせて見せよう
How noble...
なんと気丈な
そのはかなくも小さいお体で姫君は　この百年もの間
With her tiny, fragile body,
how much of her life has she abandoned?
どれだけのものを諦め
耐え忍んでいらしてきたのか
How much has she suffered?
姫君
Princess, actually...
実は
No, never mind.
いえ　なんでもありませぬ
これ以上のことはとても
I can say no more.
Let me go! I said to let me go!
離せ　離さぬか
おやめください　家重様
Stop this, Ieshige-sama!
Don't stand in my way!
邪魔立てするな
先ほどまでの蟲人についての会議の内容を　俺にも話すがよい
Tell me what was said about the insects
in the conference you just held!
But that meeting was secret...
しかし　あの会議は内々のものでして
I don't care!
知るか　すべては仁兵衛のため
I'm doing this for Jinbei!
I must tell Jinbei!
俺は仁兵衛に伝えねばならんのだ
あの声の者は
Who is that?
【仁兵衛】
息子の家重でしょう
It must be my son, Ieshige.
【仁兵衛　仁兵衛に伝えるのじゃ】
Jinbei... I must tell Jinbei!
月島
Tsukishima?
ご存知ですか　姫君
Princess, you know the man
月島という蟲奉行所の同心のことを
of the Magistrate's Office
called Tsukishima Jinbei?
I never expected to see that
expression on the Princess's face.
まさか　姫君がこのようなお顔をされるとは
吉宗公　そなたのご子息とお話をさせてもらえるとありがたい
Lord Yoshimune, I would like
to speak with your son.
家重と
With Ieshige?
No Girls Allowed
【女人　立ち入り禁止】
I never thought you'd come to
see me, Insect Magistrate.
よもや貴様のほうから俺に会いに来るとはな　蟲奉行
Did you gather all these, Ieshige-dono?
これらのものは　すべて家重殿が集められたのか
いかにも
Indeed!
この部屋には　古今東西の膨大な知識が蓄えられておる
This room contains all the
wisdom of the ages.
そしてその知識は　すべてこの俺の英知の糧となっておるのだ
And all this knowledge helps me grow wise.
What's this?
これは
それは飛騨高山に伝わるあやかしの伝説をまとめた書物だ
That is a collection of legends of
monsters from Hidatakayama.
あやかしの伝説
Legends of monsters...
This girl is trying to steal my knowledge,
小娘が　この俺の英知を盗もうとしておるのだろうが　そうはいかん
but I won't let her!
ほう　閃いた
I have it!
逆に貴様の持っているあらゆる情報を搾り取ってやるわ
Instead, I'll take all your knowledge.
そう　すべては
Yes, I'm doing all this for Jinbei!
仁兵衛のため
用はほかでもない
I'm here for one reason.
家重殿は月島仁兵衛とどういう間柄なのだ
I wish to know your relationship
to Tsukishima Jinbei.
き　貴様がなぜ仁兵衛を知っている
H-How do you know Jinbei?
同じ蟲奉行の勤め　すこし縁があってな
He works at the Magistrate's Office.
We're connected.
Connected?!
縁
B-But then, why ask me about Jinbei?
だ　だとしても　なぜ俺に仁兵衛のことを聞く
そなたも本来は月島仁兵衛と触れ合える身分ではないはず
Your rank is not such that
you should associate with
Tsukishima Jinbei, either.
自分の身分を偽ったうえで　月島との間柄を築いておるのか
Have you been lying about your
position to meet with him?
そ　それがどうした
Wh-What of it?
I see...
そうか
If you lie about your status,
you can still have a relationship.
身分を偽ったままでも　間柄は築けるものなのか
なるほど　そういうことか
So that's it...
つまりこいつは　俺と同じく仁兵衛に身分を明かせぬ口なのだな
Like me, she cannot tell Jinbei her true identity.
よかろう　そういうことなら話は別だ
Very well! That changes things.
ついてくるがいい
Follow me.
貴様と俺はいわば同士
In a way, you and I are comrades...
貴様にいいものを見せてやろう
I have something to show you.
ここからは蟲奉行所の方角がよく見える
From here, you can clearly
see the Magistrate's Office.
俺はこうやって毎日　ここから仁兵衛を眺めているのだ
I watch Jinbei every day from this place...
【仁兵衛が笑った】
So he's the next Shogun?
これが次期将軍か　未来は不安だな
I fear for the future.
Oh, look... He tripped!
【仁兵衛が扱けた】
な　なんだと
Wh-What?!
What's wrong?
どうした　月島に何があったのか
Has something happened to Tsukishima?
そんな　バカな
No! Impossible!
I'm s-sorry...
す　すみません　転んじゃいました
I tripped...
I'm g-glad you're all right.
ご　ご無事で何よりです
兄ちゃん　うらやましいね
I'm jealous, kid.
まったく　月島　何やってんのよ
Jeez... Tsukishima, what are you doing?
You wanted to hear what
happened while you were away.
休み中の話聞きたいって言うから　皆で来てやったのに
That's why we're here.
め　面目ない
I'm s-so sorry...
それで皆さん　休みの三日間はどちらで修行されたんですか
So what did you all do
during your vacation?
私は忍びの修行をしながら　いろいろ爆弾開発してきたわ
I went to the ninja village to train,
and worked on some
new kinds of explosives.
俺は別に
Nothing special here.
I was getting rusty,
ずいぶん勘が鈍ってたからよ
そこら辺のでけぇ山賊連中をぶった切ってきただけだぜ
so I found all the major bandits
in the area and cut them up.
僕は　秘密
I... It's a secret.
That's just wonderful!
なんとなんと　素晴らしい
自分ももっと精進しなければ
I must work harder, too!
That's right...
まったくだ
このバカ息子には　もったいないほどの先輩方だ
These people are too good for you.
ち　父上　いつからそこに
F-Father?
How long have you been here?
その身の熟し　出身は紀州方面かな
From the way you move,
you must be from Kishuu, right?
I see!
なるほど　剣の極意はありとあらゆるものを切ってこそ　ですか
So you believe a true master of the blade
should be able to slice anything.
土御門は衰退しきったと聞いていたが
I'd heard that Tsuchimikado wasn't
nearly as strong as it once was,
お若いのに　大したものだ
but you're quite powerful for your age.
機会があれば　ぜひ皆さんと手合せしたいものですな
Someday, I'd love to have the chance to fight you.
Jinbei-sama... Everyone...
仁兵衛様　皆様　お茶のお代わりいかがですか
Would you like some more tea?
す　素晴らしい
S-Splendid!
御嬢さん　ぜひ　家のせがれの嫁に来ないか
Miss, would you like to marry my son?
M-Marry him?
よ　嫁だ
F-Father?
ち　父上
その器量　是非に　是非に
You're so beautiful... Please! Please!
あ　あの　でも私
U-Um, but I...
It's so sudden...
そんな急に言われても
よかったじゃない　月島
Isn't that nice, Tsukishima?
Miss, there's no dumpling on that stick.
嬢ちゃん　その串　団子ついてねぇぞ
What is it?
どうした
Is that peach-boob woman
trying to trick Jinbei again?!
またあの桃乳女が仁兵衛を誑かしておるのか
思えば　妻の叶との出会いもこの江戸であったな
Come to think of it, I met my wife,
Kanae, in Edo, as well.
まあ　奥様と
You met your wife here?
馴れ初め　お聞きしたいです
I'd love to hear about it.
母上と…江戸で
You met my mother in Edo?
父上　思えば自分は　母上のことをよく知りません
Father...
I realize I don't know much of my mother.
そうか
Oh...
お前が物心ついた時には　叶はもういなかったからな
By the time you were old enough to
recognize faces, she wasn't around.
教えてください　母上とは　どのような方だったのですか
Please tell me... What was she like?
目を瞑れば　今でも思い出す
If I close my eyes, I can still see her.
叶
Kanae...
She was another sword fighter
who aspired to be Japan's best.
あやつも日の本一を目指す剣豪の一人だった
そして　あやつも抜群な胸の持ち主だった
And she had incredibly huge cans, too!
Did he remember his wife after
seeing this girl's breasts?
まさか　このおっさん人の胸見て奥さん思い出したのか
What scum...
くずね
大人のくずだ
He's scum.
That was about sixteen years ago.
あれはそう　今から大体十五六年ぐらい昔の話だ
You're going to keep going?!
まだ続けんの
俺達は武者修行の中
We met in Edo,
when we were both training with the sword.
16 Years Earlier
一人の剣客同士として　この江戸で出会ったのだ
わしは津軽出身　月島源十郎
I am Tsukishima Genjuurou, of Tsugaru!
飛騨高山出身　叶
I am Kanae, of Hidatakayama.
この江戸に無敵の剣客がいるとは聞いていたが
I'd heard that Edo had an invincible swordsman.
まさかお主のような華奢な女子だったとはな
I didn't expect it to be a slender,
elegant lady like you.
私も似たような噂は聞いていたが
I'd heard the same rumors.
But I didn't expect it to be such
a wimpy, insect-like man.
よもや　主のような優男だったとはな
We could both tell at a glance that
the other was a splendid fighter.
互いに凄腕の使い手であることは　見ただけで分かった
A single moment's weakness
would cost my life.
一瞬たりとも　隙を見せれば　命取りそうだ
We both looked for the moment to strike,
俺達は互いに相手を探りあい
そして…
and then...
こうして俺達は　夫婦になった
And so, we got married.
以上
The end.
はぁ？何でそうなるのよ
Huh?! How?
話がぶっ飛び過ぎだろうが
You left out some steps.
確かにあやつはとことんぶっとんだやつだったわい
She was a crazy girl.
Taste my special attack!
受けてみよう　わが奥義
月島流　富嶽鉄槌割り
Tsukishima-style: Mt. Fuji Hammer!
Wh-What power...
な　なんたる剛健
I'll end this here!
一気に押し切る　月島流
Tsukishima-style...
月島流
な　何が起こってんだ
Wh-What's happening?!
まさか　一度見ただけで技を盗むとは
She stole my technique after seeing it once?
なんというセンス
What skill!
I didn't expect that you'd be
able to keep up with me!
貴様こそ　この私と互角に渡り合えるとはな
I've never had so much fun, Tsukishima Genjuurou!
こんなに楽しいのははじめてたぞ　月島源十郎
わしもだ　叶
Me, neither, Kanae!
Wh-What are they?
な　何なんだ　あいつらは
I've decided, Genjuurou...
決めたぞ　源十郎
仁兵衛という名はどうだ
How about the name "Jinbei"?
I like it!
よい響きだ
He's our child...
私達二人の子だ
健やかで逞しい子に違いない
He'll grow up to be a healthy, strong boy.
I'm sure the days we spend teaching
主と二人でわが子に剣を教えあう日々は
our son to fight will be joyous ones...
きっときっと至福であろうな
た　戦いながらプロポーズって
H-He proposed as they fought?
月島の親らしいわね
That sounds like Tsukishima's dad...
素敵なお話
That's a wonderful story!
で　その勝負は結局どっちが勝ったんだ
So who ended up winning?
それから約一年ほど戦ったが
We fought for another year,
but it never ended...
決着はつかんかった
い　一年？
A y-year?
そのうち　仁兵衛が生まれたのだ
And during that time, Jinbei was born.
はぁ？
な　何と　何と何と
Wh-What? What? What?
そりゃ驚くわよね
That's pretty surprising...
父上も母上も　そのようにすごいお方だったとは
I had no idea my mother and father
were such amazing people.
I'm so fired up!
燃えてきた
こうしてはいられない
I must get started!
自分も父上母上のように　もっともっと強くならねば
I need to be stronger,
like my mother and father!
We never did get to raise him together,
結局わしら二人で育てるという望みは叶わんかったが
but don't worry, Kanae.
だが叶　安心するがいい
He's a dumb kid,
バカだが
お前の望んだ通り　育っているぞ
but he's growing up just the way you'd hoped.
What's wrong?
どうした
Are you done?
もう気が済んだのか
家重殿　そなたに聞きたいことがある
Ieshige-dono, I want to ask you something.
What?
何だ
吉宗公が宝を隠すとすれば　どこに隠す
If Lord Yoshimune were going to hide
a treasure, where would he hide it?
宝だと
A treasure?
まさか貴様　赤城山中にあると伝えられる
You can't be after the Tokugawa's buried treasure,
徳川家の埋蔵金を狙っておるのではなかろうな
said to be hidden in the Akagi Mountains!
金塊などに興味はない
I've no interest in gold.
わらわが知りたいのは　蟲に関するある伝説だ
What I want to know is a
legend about the insects.
伝説？
A legend?
蟲に関する伝説か
A legend about the insects...
いや　ひょっとすると…
I might know just the place!
No! No! No! No! No! No!
違う　違う　違う　違う　違う　違う
これだ
This is it!
これはかつて　俺が蟲奉行所の書庫に忍び込んだ時に得た情報だ
This is the information I attained by sneaking
into the Insect Magistrate's library.
見たものは全て忘れろと言われていたが
They said to forget everything I'd seen,
黙って引き下がる俺ではない
but I would not do that!
Using my memory, I made an exact replica!
あの時の記憶を頼りに　まったく同じものを作ってやったわ
そして見ろ 西日本各地には全て蟲のしるしが書かれておるが
And look!
The insect's sign is written
all over western Japan.
But east of Kishuu, no mark is made!
紀州より東は一つもない
これは紀州が　蟲に対する最大な防壁となっておるからだ
That is because Kishuu is our greatest
defense against the insects.
貴様のいう伝説が何かは知らぬが
I don't know this legend of which you speak,
父上が宝を隠すとなれば
but if my father were going
to hide some treasure,
蟲の侵攻からもっとも離れた場所
he'd put it as far away
from the insects' advance as possible:
here, the distant land of Ezo!
すなわち　最果ての地　蝦夷に違いない
Insect
Kishuu, then?
紀州か
Sarutobi Sasuke's body has disappeared?
猿飛佐助の死骸が　消えただと
は　はい
Yes.
どうやら何者かの手で持ち去られたようで
Someone seems to have taken it.
Could it have been the other Insect-men?
まさか　他の蟲人共が
I-It appears I underestimated the enemy,
しょ　少々敵を侮って…いたようだ
but I'm safe now.
助かった
What are you talking about, weakling?
弱者が何を語っておる
Why would I save you?
やつらに情報を与えないためとはいえ
I merely wished to avoid
giving them information.
なぜこの拙者がお主如きのために
S-Stop it...
や　やめっ
霧隠才蔵…殿
Kirigakure Saizou, you...
Don't make me waste effort on you,
手間をかけさせおって　この屑蟲が
Ten Crucifix Insects
Kirigakure Saizou
you dung beetle.
I must also hurry...
拙者も急ぎ参らねばなるまい
To Kishuu, where Yukimura-sama awaits.
幸村様の待つ　紀州へ
So why did you wish to speak with me?
それで　わたしくにお話とは…
Regarding a way to regain my power.
わらわの力を取り戻す術についてだ
There is no time to waste.
もはや一刻の猶予もない
You know that.
そなたも分かっておるであろう
B-But...
し　しかし…
Insect
Kishuu, isn't it?
紀州だな
You will tell me everything
you know, Lord Yoshimune.
話してもらうぞ　吉宗公
そなたの知る全てを
Y-Yes.
はい
Then, to regain my power,
I must go to that well myself, yes?
では　力を取り戻すにはわらわ自らがその井戸に出向ねばならぬのだな
Yes.
はい
分かった
I understand.
Then I shall leave at once.
ならばすぐにでも出立致そう
A moment.
お待ちを
We don't know what threat
awaits on the road...
道中　どのような危険が待ち構えているやも分かりませぬ
With your power gone,
力を失った今の姫君には
heading there alone would be wrong.
たった一人で向かわれるのは　バツです
If you're going in secret,
I ask that you take me,
極秘の隠密道中とあらば
ぜひこの江戸南町奉行 大岡越前守忠相を　お供としてお連れください
Oooka Echizen no Kamitadasuke,
of the Edo Southtown Magistrate's.
そなたを？
Who are you?
Princess, as you know,
姫もご存知の通り
Oooka is one of my most trusted men.
大岡はわが懐刀
The smartest man in Edo,
and a master of the blade.
江戸一番の切れ者にして　剣の達人である
この者ならば　姫の護衛として十分に役に立つでしょう
He will be the perfect guard for you.
うむ
All right.
Then I'd prefer that another
ならばもう一人　蟲奉行所より供をつけたい
from the Insect Magistrate's accompany me.
How much longer?
【後どのくらいなの】
Kotori-dono told me to hurry here,
to wait for someone...
小鳥殿に急ぎここで人を待つように言われてきたものの
But I don't see anyone
who looks like the right person.
それらしき人が誰もいない
I may have gotten the place wrong.
もしや場所を間違えたのかも
案ずるな
Do not worry.
I am already here.
既に来ておる
You are...
あなたは…
That servant!
お付の方
では参ろうか　紀州へ
Let us go to Kishuu.
紀　紀州へ
T-To Kishuu?!
I keep my mind and body pure at all times,
Next Time
自分は蟲奉行様にお会いする時のため
常に見も心も清めております
so that I may meet the Magistrate.
そう　例えるなら火鉢殿の純白のふんどしのように
Yes, you could say they're like
Hibachi-dono's pure white fundoshi.
例えるな
Don't say that!
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
次回蟲奉行「クールなメガネの○×講座」
The Cool Guy in Glasses
Lectures on Right and Wrong.
Lectures on Right and Wrong